#### Contact

gingerkingmsn@yahoo.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ginger-king-dnp (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

Healthcare Healthcare Management Hospitals

## Languages

English

### Certifications

Certified Nurse Manager and Leader Certified Emergency Nurse

# Ginger King, DNP, RN, CEN, CNML

Director of Nursing- Acute Care Services at Methodist Health System Dallas/Fort Worth Area

### Summary

Experienced Director with a demonstrated history of working in the hospital & health care industry. Skilled in Healthcare Management, Healthcare, Patient Safety, Nursing, and Medical-Surgical. Strong professional with a Doctorate of Nursing Practice focused in Executive Leadership.

## Experience

Methodist Health System
Director
May 2019 - Present (1 year 1 month)
Dallas, Texas

CHRISTUS Trinity Mother Frances Health System
Director
November 2015 - May 2019 (3 years 7 months)
Tyler, Texas Area

Director of Medical ICU, Surgical ICU, Trauma ICU, Intermediate Care Unit, and Vascular Access at a Level II Trauma Hospital. Hospital liason for Dialysis

Cedars-Sinai Manager May 2013 - November 2015 (2 years 7 months) Greater Los Angeles Area

Provided overall leadership and management of operations for a 64 bed critical care cardiac unit within a non-profit, community-based, internationally acclaimed organization. Accountable for managing human resource/personnel, clinical and fiscal aspects of defined areas of responsibility, including five supervisors (CNIV) who supervise and lead approximately 180 FTEs. In close conjunction with the CNO, responsible for implementing administrative best practices to assist with the organization's non-profit capacity building efforts. Ensure compliance with all applicable IRS, federal, state, county and city

regulations. Accountable for clinical practice standards of care, policy and procedures, and performance improvement initiatives.

Montefiore
Supervisor
October 2009 - May 2013 (3 years 8 months)
Bronx, New York

Responsible for implementing and managing patient care full time in a high-volume New York City Emergency Department environment in a facility of 1469 beds; providing care for a patient population from pediatric through geriatric age levels. Consistently worked extra hours per diem in organization's Ambulatory Surgery, providing pre and post-surgical care for the pediatric and adult population, in times of high census. Assumed Charge Nurse and preceptor responsibilities as directed. Served as Delegate for New York State Nursing Association, responsible for being a liaison between employees and the hospital organization, as well as conducting and participation in union meetings and campaigns. Organized a Unit Performance Council for the Emergency Department and presented to administration for house-wide implementation. Actively participated and collaborated for multiple organizational projects including changes to triage workflow process, EMR implementation, and new employee training.

Danbury Hospital Manager June 2009 - August 2010 (1 year 3 months) Danbury, Connecticut

Provided clinical expertise for all patient care delivery and nursing standards in a 30 bed intensive care unit and cardio-thoracic intensive care unit in a regional level II 371 bed trauma center. Maintained clinical competence in areas of expertise and partnered with nursing education to assist in maintaining staff competencies and promoting nursing education and clinical skills. • Promoted performance improvement philosophy and practices. Gathered performance improvement data to identify, monitor, and evaluate processes. In conjunction with manager, identified and facilitated change initiative to improve outcomes. Accountable for unit operations on a 24/7 basis, including maintaining a budget for the unit with financial awareness incorporated into daily practice, including resource allocation, patient care management, unit staffing utilization, and integration of legal and risk management principles into practice and unit operations with 109 FTE's.

Participated in the hiring, coaching, conducting performance evaluations, and counseling of employees, including disciplinary action as appropriate. Delivered direct patient care when needed, and taught BLS certification and recertification classes to employees.

Ascension Health
Charge RN/ House Supervisor/ Registered Nurse
December 2000 - August 2009 (8 years 9 months)
Jacksonville, Florida

Began career as a nursing assistant and served as a preceptor to new employees and nursing students and assumed charge nurse position as assigned in a 528 bed facility. Ensured efficient quality of care was provided and compliant with federal, state and local regulatory requirements and established organizational goals. Served as a department nurse leader and expert in the application process and the delivery of patient care. Worked with Nurse Management to address issues identified with regard to quality of care standards, as well as served on various organization committees. In collaboration with Nurse Manager or Assistant Nurse Manager, ensured adequate staffing and time schedules were managed within budgetary standard. Responsibilities included authorization of overtime or scheduling changes to fill shifts as necessary and bed flow coordination as house supervisor. Worked in cardiac cath lab, PACU, PACO, ICU, ER, and telemetry.

### **HCA**

Bariatric Coordinator/Registered Nurse August 2004 - June 2009 (4 years 11 months) Jacksonville, Florida Area

Responsible for patient care in a complex environment; providing care for populations of pediatric through geriatric age levels in a 425 bed facility. Responsible for the monitoring and management of surgical recovery inpatients (PACU) who have gone under regional or general anesthesia; including vascular, cardio-thoracic, ENT, GI, urological, and neurological cases. Served as a preceptor in training new employees, trained multiple departments in computerized charting, and assumed charge nurse responsibilities. Developed outpatient surgical program for bariatric surgery at Jacksonville Surgery Center including: Program development, clinical management and care coordination of outpatient bariatric surgery program, development and maintenance of a dedicated bariatric website, establishing

and maintaining a multi-specialty referral network for bariatric patients, as well as development of surgical best practices and policies, and providing patient education and consultations, developing and conducting seminars and support group meetings, oversight of multidisciplinary team meetings, staff education, risk management, insurance approval and verifications, oversight and maintaining Center of Excellence guidelines and compliance, as well as implementing and practicing key business and financial principles to improve surgical volume and optimize a profitable business model. Coordinated outpatient bariatric surgery center services for 6 surgical bed surgery center, providing high quality, individualized patient care and supporting HCA organizational philosophies.

## Education

**Grand Canyon University** 

Doctor of Nursing Practice, Executive Leadership · (2017 - 2019)

Sacred Heart University

Master of Science Nursing, Nursing Leadership and Healthcare Services · (2012 - 2014)

Chamberlain College of Nursing

Bachelor of Science Nursing, Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse · (2008 - 2010)

Florida State College at Jacksonville

Associate of Arts and Sciences (A.A.S.), Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse · (1998 - 2000)